<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-07T02:33:21-05:00</updated><id>https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Gagan Sharma’s Blog</title><subtitle>Musings on tech, ideas and life</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Notes on Learning</title><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/01/28/learning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Learning" /><published>2020-01-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-01-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/01/28/learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/01/28/learning.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;notes-on-learning&quot;&gt;Notes on Learning&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-absorb-information-faster-and-retain-for-longer&quot;&gt;How to absorb information faster and retain for longer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a compiled set of tools that I have gathered from various sources to help in the process of learning. You can 
use it as a framework to tackle any learning assignment. There are a ton of material out there and I have included only the
ones that have helped me immensely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;before-study&quot;&gt;Before Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design a near-optimal environment that you’re comfortable with.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try Airplane mode on phone.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try noise-cancelling headphones.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try ambient background music to help in concentration (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.noisli.com&quot;&gt;noisli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brain.fm&quot;&gt;brain.fm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://coderadio.freecodecamp.org/&quot;&gt;freecodecamp-radio&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design the study sessions along the lines of &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/deliberate-practice-theory&quot;&gt;Deliberate practice&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Find material which is not too easy, nor too hard but at a level that pushes you to exercise your brain without requiring advanced skills.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Model your self-education around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fast.ai/2016/10/08/teaching-philosophy/&quot;&gt;these principles&lt;/a&gt;. Diversify your resources.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Focus on applications first when starting out, then learn the theory as and when needed. Example: If you’re trying to learn Deep Learning, try building some models first and then learn the theory behind it, as taught in the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;course.fast.ai&quot;&gt;Fast.ai course&lt;/a&gt;.
Another example: If you’re trying to learn a second language, try speaking useful phrases before learning grammar.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Learn by doing. Build things. Get actively involved in the process.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;during-study&quot;&gt;During Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Divide your study sessions into chunks of 25 minutes of focused work followed by 5 minutes of break. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&quot;&gt;Pomodoro method&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forestapp.cc/&quot;&gt;Forest app&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take notes while you study. Type/write the words out in your note-taking app/notebook instead of copy-pasting or capturing images.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simultaneously create flashcards to use spaced-repetition. &lt;a href=&quot;https://quantum.country&quot;&gt;This website on learning quantum computing&lt;/a&gt; incorporated spaced-repetition into the learning material. You can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.ankiweb.net/&quot;&gt;Anki&lt;/a&gt; for your personal notes. The app would take care of your repetitions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to incorporate visual mnemonics while learning. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nelsondellis.com/remember-it&quot;&gt;Nelson Dellis’ excellent book&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLnoNZatRUaRwFphlCMbwJeXuYg-AoE6t1&quot;&gt;his youtube channel&lt;/a&gt; will get you covered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most importantly, &lt;strong&gt;Pause and Ponder&lt;/strong&gt; (a phrase taken from videos by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.3blue1brown.com/&quot;&gt;Grant Sanderson&lt;/a&gt;). Think in analogies and reflect on the intuitive meaning to deepen the conceptual understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;after-study&quot;&gt;After Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review often. If you use Anki, this will be taken care of automatically. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://augmentingcognition.com/ltm.html&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jackkinsella.ie/articles/janki-method-refined&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. If you don’t use Anki or any spaced-repetition software, schedule your reviews in 1, 3, 7, 21, 45, … days. (This is what I used before moving to Anki. You can try your own schedules.) See &lt;a href=&quot;https://collegeinfogeek.com/spaced-repetition-memory-technique/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourawesomememory.com/spaced-repetition-overview/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recall trumps re-reading. When you’re reviewing, try to recall the material instead of just reading/watching/listening it again. Familiarity gives us a false sense of knowledge. Test yourself while reviewing to help in retention. Barbara Oakley’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://barbaraoakley.com/books/a-mind-for-numbers/&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn/&quot;&gt;course&lt;/a&gt; are amazing resources which delve deep into this concept and other study techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/2012/04/feynman-technique/&quot;&gt;Feynman technique&lt;/a&gt; for reinforcing what you learned:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pretend you are teaching it to a student.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Identify gaps in your explanation;  Go back to the source material, to better understand it. Also, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_f-qkGJBPts&quot;&gt;see this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to apply what you’ve learned to concrete problems to help cement your concepts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have fun learning!!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Notes on Learning How to absorb information faster and retain for longer</summary></entry></feed>