<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-04T13:22:10-05:00</updated><id>https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Gagan Sharma’s Blog</title><subtitle>Musings on tech, ideas and life</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Essense of Incerto</title><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/09/04/essence-of-incerto.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Essense of Incerto" /><published>2020-09-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/09/04/essence-of-incerto</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/09/04/essence-of-incerto.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently finished reading the “Incerto”, a multi-volume part autobiography and part exploration of chance, randomness, probability and luck, written by Nassim Nicholas Taleb. The title of this article sounds provocative as it should be. Its difficult to distill “essence” of multi-volume books in a short listicle. But this article’s &lt;i&gt;telos&lt;/i&gt; is to document my own personal insights and learnings that I have gathered by reading Taleb’s books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We underestimate the role of chance in our success and overestimate it in our failures. (Fooled by Randomness). Successful people are generally simply “lucky”. However, unsuccessful people might not be just “unlucky”. Sure, most hard-working folks will be. But you can be “unskilled” more than “unlucky”. I personally think that we can only minimise the risk of failures by making effort in the direction of our success.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The more risks a gambler takes, the closer they get to “ruin”. Similarly, the more risks I take, I decrease my chances of survival. Corollary: If I take stupid risks, I would be “ruined” faster than &lt;i&gt;predicted&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We cannot completely be sure of our successes (because of Black Swan events which are rare and never observed until they happen) but we can prepare for failures. Plan like a pessimist, hope like an optimist. Being robust to unpredictable events is essential to survival. Negative Black Swans cannot be predicted but failure to build a system which can withstand them is a catastrophe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Becoming Antifragile(where we benefit from disorder and rare events) is as simple as mitigating negative Black Swan events by being robust to them and taking multiple &lt;i&gt;small&lt;/i&gt;risks in favor of positive Black Swans (The barbell strategy)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I take a risk, and I enjoy the fruits of its success, then its failures should also be borne by me. (Skin in the Game). One should not be antifragile at the expense of the fragility of others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Via Negativa: Less is more: Subtraction is the key: Make the risk of ruin ZERO and reduce the loss in the positive risks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small amount of randomness is essential to life otherwise it becomes monotonous. This randomness acts as an antifragile agent. But too much of volatility is detrimental hence a balance must be maintained. Its just like vaccine doses: Build up immunity by small doses of infections but a large infection will probably kill you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extremistan vs Mediocristan: Extremes vs mediocrities: A dentist has a limited income, and all dentists in a definite geographical area would have a “ranged” income. Au contraire, an author can have potentially unlimited income. However such authors are rare. An average dentist earns similar to or perhaps more than the average author. But on the extremes, some authors live in penury and some in mansions. Corollary: Scandals never hurt artists because they are in extremistan and the unbounded information flow can potentially open up opportunities. Corollary: Having a small “tribe” of followers and huge number of critics is more beneficial than everyone saying your work is “good”. Again, because of how extremes behave.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Respecting the ancient: What has survived for long is more likely to survive for longer(Lindy Effect). People create rituals and religions as a means to an end. Take that away and chaos ensues. Besides, what people “believe” and “do” are vastly different, as in the Pope wouldn’t go to the church instead of the doctor in case of a medical problem. Survival is essential for science, not the other way around. To avoid clashes of cultures, Commerce and trade is one easy way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently finished reading the “Incerto”, a multi-volume part autobiography and part exploration of chance, randomness, probability and luck, written by Nassim Nicholas Taleb. The title of this article sounds provocative as it should be. Its difficult to distill “essence” of multi-volume books in a short listicle. But this article’s telos is to document my own personal insights and learnings that I have gathered by reading Taleb’s books.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Installing the Fastai library on Windows 10</title><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/06/03/fastai-windows.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Installing the Fastai library on Windows 10" /><published>2020-06-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/06/03/fastai-windows</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/06/03/fastai-windows.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;installing-the-fastai-library-on-windows-10&quot;&gt;Installing the Fastai library on Windows 10&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the steps I took to install fastai v2 on my windows machine. This version of fastai is still in development as of 3rd of June,
2020 so I would recommend using v1 instead for production. (But then, would you use windows for production ? ;) )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-the-instructions-at-httpsdevfastai-to-install-an-editable-version&quot;&gt;Use the instructions at https://dev.fast.ai/ to install an editable version&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/fastai/fastai2
cd fastai2
conda env create -f environment.yml
source activate fastai2
pip install -e &quot;.[dev]&quot;

git clone https://github.com/fastai/fastcore
cd fastcore
pip install -e &quot;.[dev]&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above commands should install both fastai and fastcore in editable mode. So, if you update one, remember to update the other as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heres-what-i-tried-after-installing&quot;&gt;Here’s what I tried after installing:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;from fastai2.vision.all import *
path = untar_data(URLs.PETS)/'images'

def is_cat(x): return x[0].isupper()
dls = ImageDataLoaders.from_name_func(
    path, get_image_files(path), valid_pct=0.2, seed=42,
    label_func=is_cat, item_tfms=Resize(224), num_workers=0)

learn = cnn_learner(dls, resnet34, metrics=error_rate)
from PIL import ImageFile
ImageFile.LOAD_TRUNCATED_IMAGES = True
learn.fine_tune(1)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an RTX 2060 in my machine and training took 256 seconds compared to Google Colaboratory which took 89 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-to-note&quot;&gt;Things to Note&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you see a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CUDA Runtime Error&lt;/code&gt;, set the  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;num_workers = 0&lt;/code&gt; in the dataloader function.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;OSError: Image file is truncated&lt;/code&gt; , use this piece of code
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;from PIL import ImageFile
ImageFile.LOAD_TRUNCATED_IMAGES = True
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would try to add more points here once I explore further.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Installing the Fastai library on Windows 10</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on Learning</title><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/01/28/learning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Learning" /><published>2020-01-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-01-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/01/28/learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/01/28/learning.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;notes-on-learning&quot;&gt;Notes on Learning&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-absorb-information-faster-and-retain-for-longer&quot;&gt;How to absorb information faster and retain for longer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a compiled set of tools that I have gathered from various sources to help in the process of learning. You can 
use it as a framework to tackle any learning assignment. There are a ton of material out there and I have included only the
ones that have helped me immensely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;before-study&quot;&gt;Before Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design a near-optimal environment that you’re comfortable with.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try Airplane mode on phone.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try noise-cancelling headphones.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try ambient background music to help in concentration (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.noisli.com&quot;&gt;noisli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brain.fm&quot;&gt;brain.fm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://coderadio.freecodecamp.org/&quot;&gt;freecodecamp-radio&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design the study sessions along the lines of &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/deliberate-practice-theory&quot;&gt;Deliberate practice&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Find material which is not too easy, nor too hard but at a level that pushes you to exercise your brain without requiring advanced skills.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Model your self-education around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fast.ai/2016/10/08/teaching-philosophy/&quot;&gt;these principles&lt;/a&gt;. Diversify your resources.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Focus on applications first when starting out, then learn the theory as and when needed. Example: If you’re trying to learn Deep Learning, try building some models first and then learn the theory behind it, as taught in the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;course.fast.ai&quot;&gt;Fast.ai course&lt;/a&gt;.
Another example: If you’re trying to learn a second language, try speaking useful phrases before learning grammar.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Learn by doing. Build things. Get actively involved in the process.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;during-study&quot;&gt;During Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Divide your study sessions into chunks of 25 minutes of focused work followed by 5 minutes of break. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&quot;&gt;Pomodoro method&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forestapp.cc/&quot;&gt;Forest app&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take notes while you study. Type/write the words out in your note-taking app/notebook instead of copy-pasting or capturing images.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simultaneously create flashcards to use spaced-repetition. &lt;a href=&quot;https://quantum.country&quot;&gt;This website on learning quantum computing&lt;/a&gt; incorporated spaced-repetition into the learning material. You can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.ankiweb.net/&quot;&gt;Anki&lt;/a&gt; for your personal notes. The app would take care of your repetitions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to incorporate visual mnemonics while learning. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nelsondellis.com/remember-it&quot;&gt;Nelson Dellis’ excellent book&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLnoNZatRUaRwFphlCMbwJeXuYg-AoE6t1&quot;&gt;his youtube channel&lt;/a&gt; will get you covered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most importantly, &lt;strong&gt;Pause and Ponder&lt;/strong&gt; (a phrase taken from videos by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.3blue1brown.com/&quot;&gt;Grant Sanderson&lt;/a&gt;). Think in analogies and reflect on the intuitive meaning to deepen the conceptual understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;after-study&quot;&gt;After Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review often. If you use Anki, this will be taken care of automatically. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://augmentingcognition.com/ltm.html&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jackkinsella.ie/articles/janki-method-refined&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. If you don’t use Anki or any spaced-repetition software, schedule your reviews in 1, 3, 7, 21, 45, … days. (This is what I used before moving to Anki. You can try your own schedules.) See &lt;a href=&quot;https://collegeinfogeek.com/spaced-repetition-memory-technique/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourawesomememory.com/spaced-repetition-overview/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recall trumps re-reading. When you’re reviewing, try to recall the material instead of just reading/watching/listening it again. Familiarity gives us a false sense of knowledge. Test yourself while reviewing to help in retention. Barbara Oakley’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://barbaraoakley.com/books/a-mind-for-numbers/&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn/&quot;&gt;course&lt;/a&gt; are amazing resources which delve deep into this concept and other study techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/2012/04/feynman-technique/&quot;&gt;Feynman technique&lt;/a&gt; for reinforcing what you learned:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pretend you are teaching it to a student.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Identify gaps in your explanation;  Go back to the source material, to better understand it. Also, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_f-qkGJBPts&quot;&gt;see this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to apply what you’ve learned to concrete problems to help cement your concepts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have fun learning!!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Notes on Learning How to absorb information faster and retain for longer</summary></entry></feed>