<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-12T06:55:57-05:00</updated><id>https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Gagan Sharma’s Blog</title><subtitle>Musings on tech, ideas and life</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Super Thinking</title><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/09/12/superthinking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Super Thinking" /><published>2020-09-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/09/12/superthinking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/09/12/superthinking.html">&lt;p&gt;Super Thinking is one of the best books I have read recently. It acts as a compendium of multiple tools and techniques that can help in exapanding one’s thinking capabilities.
The book is written by Lauren McCann , a statistician and researcher with numerous medical publications to her name. Her co-author Gabriel Weinberg is the CEO of the internet search company DuckDuckGo, which is a privacy focused browser(it does not track you like google).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;essence-of-the-book&quot;&gt;Essence of the book&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tried to document a few actionable insights that I gained from the book. Please note that these are my own thoughts and ideas that were influenced by the book or pre-existing ideas that were refined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;matrix-models-for-decisions&quot;&gt;Matrix-Models for decisions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever faced with a dilemma regarding choices, matrix-models can be quite helpful.  As in a mathematical matrix, we create a box-like structure and evaluate our choices based on the options. We could have cost vs benefit or pros vs cons when choosing between choices. Some prominent matrix models discussed in the book are:
Eisenhower Decision Matrix:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/thepurplingpoet/blog/blob/master/images/Eisenhower-Decision.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Consequence-Conviction Matrix:
&lt;img src=&quot;images/Consequence-Conviction.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical Candor Matrix for offering feedback:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/Radical-Candor.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;biases&quot;&gt;Biases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans unconsciously have a lot of biases. For example, people might wrongly assume that flights are not safe compared to car rides. However, statistically, car accidents occur lot more often than airplane crashes. But the media focus on the gory details of a crash more than the banal accident on the highway. And that affects our thinking. Always look out for the facts behind an opinion. And be ready to change opinions when presented with counterfactual evidence. Although this might be difficult when we’re all a part of echo chambers on social media, I’d like to stress that verifying and cross-checking “facts” is one great way to steer clear fromt he negative effects of biases. Most often, there is no black-and-white and the answer lies in a gray area. Also, correlation may not imply causation. So always be on the lookout for a “third variable”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book delves into a lot of other biases and they’re all mentioned in the takeways below. I also highly recommend reading Nobel Laureates Kahneman and Tversky’s seminal book “Thinking Fast and Slow” for further look into biases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adaptability&quot;&gt;Adaptability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being adaptive requires having multiple(but not too much) options to avoid any “path dependence”. Adaptiveness is necessary for innovation and the flexibility it lends to our lives. One key component of this is to always have an “exit strategy”. For example, if you’re starting up, and the venture blows up, you should have enough capital to survive for sometime while you look for the next opportunity. Also note that past events are not a predictor for future consequences so be ready for any eventuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “unknown unknowns” or the events that we do not know about, might occur and wreck our plans (Covid-19, anyone?). Such events, called Black Swans, can be better prepared against by incorporating a more robust scenario-analysis in our thinking. Prepare for the worst, hope for the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;productivity&quot;&gt;Productivity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becoming productive entails a few changes in our mindset which involve among other things, recognizing the value of Pareto’s 80-20 principle: 80% of rewards come from 20% of efforts. Focusing on the strong few skills that we have and reducing the 20% most distracting activities can work wonders.
Reframing a problem can help to understand more nuances which might have been previously missed. Thinking through multiple lenses and often in “other people’s shoes” can unlock patterns that bring us closer to the solution. A different framing might also help when dealing with other people. It certainly helps when companies push the same product’s advertisment but with different words to convince different demographics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These notes are almost entirely taken from the “Key Takeaways” at the end of each chapter. They are to serve as a ready reckoner to look up these notes myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;being-wrong-less&quot;&gt;Being Wrong Less&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Objective Thinking =&amp;gt; Argue from FIRST PRINCIPLES, Get to the ROOT CAUSE and seek the THIRD STORY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our views may be influenced because of AVAILABILITY BIAS, OPTIMISTIC PROBABILITY BIAS, FUNDAMENTAL ATTRIBUTION ERROR etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigate the simplest and respectful objective explanations using OCKHAM’s RAZOR and HANLON’S RAZOR and then DE-RISK those assumptions while avoiding PREMATURE-OPTIMIZATION.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;THINK IN GRAY to avoid CONFIRMATION BIAS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bypass the FILTER BUBBLE by becoming the DEVIL’S ADVOCATE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;anything-that-can-go-wrong-will&quot;&gt;Anything that can go wrong, will&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EXTERNALITIES can cause SPILLOVER EVENTS(bad health effects causing factory pollution), which can be fixed using intervention(regulation) or COASE THEOREM(such as by CAP AND TRADE)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PUBLIC GOODS (like education) are particularly susceptible to the TRAGEDY OF THE COMMONS (like poor schools) via the FREE-RIDER PROBLEM (not paying taxes)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ASYMMETRIC INFORMATION can lead to PRINCIPAL-AGENT PROBLEMS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GOODHART’S LAW=&amp;gt;rewards on measurable incentives can cause unintended consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SHORT-TERMISM can lead to TECH-DEBT and create disadvantageous PATH-DEPENDENCE, which can be mitigated by PRESERVING OPTIONALITY with PRECAUTIONARY PRINCIPLE.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decisions are REVERSIBLE AND IRREVERSIBLE. Avoid ANALYSIS PARALYSIS for the former.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heed Murphy’s Law.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spend-your-time-wisely&quot;&gt;Spend your time wisely&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow your NORTH STAR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid MULTITASKING and always have ONE IDEA AT THE TOP OF YOUR MIND&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use OPPORTUNITY COST and EISENHOWER MATRIX (urgent vs important) to select options and tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use 80/20 rule to increase LEVERAGE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stop at DIMINISHING RETURNS and avoid NEGATIVE RETURNS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use COMMITMENT and the DEFAULT EFFECT to avoid PRESENT BIAS, and PERIODIC EVALUATIONS to avoid LOSS-AVERSION and SUNK-COST FALLACY.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shortcut via DESIGN PATTERNS and ALGORITHMS and consider REFRAMING THE PROBLEM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;becoming-one-with-nature&quot;&gt;Becoming one with nature&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adopting an experimental mindset =&amp;gt; NATURAL SELECTION + SCIENTIFIC METHOD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Respect INERTIA =&amp;gt; Create/Join healthy FLYWHEELS, avoid STRATEGY TAXES unless there is a CATALYST and a lot of POTENTIAL ENERGY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reach CRITICAL MASS for TECHNOLOGY ADOPTION LIFECYCLE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;FORCING FUNCTIONS can grease the wheels for change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cultivate LUCK SURFACE AREA without getting subsumed by ENTROPY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid ZERO-SUM/BLACK-WHITE situations and look for WIN-WIN opportunities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lies-damned-lies-and-statistics&quot;&gt;Lies, Damned lies and Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid succumbing to the GAMBLER’S FALLACY or the BASE RATE FALLACY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CORRELATION DOES NOT IMPLY CAUSATION. Keep that in mind while forming HYPOTHESES based on ANECDOTAL EVIDENCE.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experiments should be RANDOMISED CONTROLLED and AB tested which can show STATISTICAL SIGNIFICANCE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NORMAL DISTRIBUTION + CENTRAL LIMIT THEOREM=&amp;gt; 68% values within 1 standard deviation, 95% within two.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;SELECTION BIAS&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;RESPONSE BIAS&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;SURVIVORSHIP BIAS in data can lead to FALSE POSITIVE or FALSE NEGATIVE.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SYSTEMATIC REVIEW or META-ANALYSIS helps in increasing confidence in a result due to replication.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calculated or reported values may be uncertain when dealing with uncertainty, hence use ERROR BARS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;decisions-decisions&quot;&gt;Decisions, Decisions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;COST-BENEFIT + DECISION TREE are better than a simple pros/cons list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To uncover key drivers, use SENSITIVITY ANALYSIS and look for any DISCOUNT RATES.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SYSTEMS THINKING + SCENARIO ANALYSIS can uncover Black Swans or unknown unknowns.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SIMULATIONS may be the best solution in cases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use LATERAL+DIVERGENT THINKING to deal with GROUPTHINK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strive to look for GLOBAL OPTIMUM and make decisions to get yourself closer to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dealing-with-conflict&quot;&gt;Dealing with Conflict&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Game Theory lens =&amp;gt; PRISONER’S DILEMMA, ULTIMATUM GAME , WAR OF ATTRITION.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Influence models =&amp;gt; RECIPROCITY + COMMITMENT + LIKING + SOCIAL PROOF + SCARCITY + AUTHORITY. Beware of DARK PATTERNS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Framing/POV =&amp;gt; SOCIAL VS MARKET NORMS, DISTRIBUTIVE VS PROCEDURAL JUSTICE, APPEAL TO EMOTION.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prefer DETERRENCE and CONTAINMENT.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change the game with GUERILLA tactics + ABOVE_THE_WEIGHT punches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be aware of the LAST WAR and know your EXIT STRATEGY.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unlocking-peoples-potential&quot;&gt;Unlocking people’s potential&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Always manage the person&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid PETER PRINCIPLE=&amp;gt; promoting to roles where they succeed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DRI =&amp;gt; directly responsible individual&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DELIBERATE PRACTICE for improvement, CONSEQUENCE-CONVICTION MATRIX for opportunites, RADICAL CANDOR for 1:1s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Watch out for DUNNING-KRUGER EFFECT and IMPOSTOR SYNDROME&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Winning Hearts and Minds is Culture :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;flex-your-market-power&quot;&gt;Flex your Market Power&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find a SECRET and build around it, searching via CUSTOMER DEVELOPMENT for PRODUCT/MARKET FIT&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Navigate the IDEA-MAZE by being a HEAT-SEEKING MISSILE, looking for RESONANT FREQUENCY for validation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find BRIGHT SPOTS or PIVOT&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a MOAT to create SUSTAINABLE COMPETITIVE ADVANTAGE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ONLY THE PARANOID SURVIVE =&amp;gt; INNOVATE DISRUPTIVELY and CROSS THE CHASM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Super Thinking is one of the best books I have read recently. It acts as a compendium of multiple tools and techniques that can help in exapanding one’s thinking capabilities. The book is written by Lauren McCann , a statistician and researcher with numerous medical publications to her name. Her co-author Gabriel Weinberg is the CEO of the internet search company DuckDuckGo, which is a privacy focused browser(it does not track you like google). Essence of the book I have tried to document a few actionable insights that I gained from the book. Please note that these are my own thoughts and ideas that were influenced by the book or pre-existing ideas that were refined. Matrix-Models for decisions Whenever faced with a dilemma regarding choices, matrix-models can be quite helpful. As in a mathematical matrix, we create a box-like structure and evaluate our choices based on the options. We could have cost vs benefit or pros vs cons when choosing between choices. Some prominent matrix models discussed in the book are: Eisenhower Decision Matrix:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Essense of Incerto</title><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/09/04/essence-of-incerto.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Essense of Incerto" /><published>2020-09-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/09/04/essence-of-incerto</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/09/04/essence-of-incerto.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently finished reading the “Incerto”, a multi-volume part autobiography and part exploration of chance, randomness, probability and luck, written by Nassim Nicholas Taleb. The title of this article sounds provocative as it should be. Its difficult to distill “essence” of multi-volume books in a short listicle. But this article’s &lt;i&gt;telos&lt;/i&gt; is to document my own personal insights and learnings that I have gathered by reading Taleb’s books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We underestimate the role of chance in our success and overestimate it in our failures. (Fooled by Randomness). Successful people are generally simply “lucky”. However, unsuccessful people might not be just “unlucky”. Sure, most hard-working folks will be. But you can be “unskilled” more than “unlucky”. I personally think that we can only minimise the risk of failures by making effort in the direction of our success.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The more risks a gambler takes, the closer they get to “ruin”. Similarly, the more risks I take, I decrease my chances of survival. Corollary: If I take stupid risks, I would be “ruined” faster than &lt;i&gt;predicted&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We cannot completely be sure of our successes (because of Black Swan events which are rare and never observed until they happen) but we can prepare for failures. Plan like a pessimist, hope like an optimist. Being robust to unpredictable events is essential to survival. Negative Black Swans cannot be predicted but failure to build a system which can withstand them is a catastrophe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Becoming Antifragile(where we benefit from disorder and rare events) is as simple as mitigating negative Black Swan events by being robust to them and taking multiple &lt;i&gt;small&lt;/i&gt;risks in favor of positive Black Swans (The barbell strategy)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I take a risk, and I enjoy the fruits of its success, then its failures should also be borne by me. (Skin in the Game). One should not be antifragile at the expense of the fragility of others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Via Negativa: Less is more: Subtraction is the key: Make the risk of ruin ZERO and reduce the loss in the positive risks. Corollary: A robust criterion for material success is the non-existence of schedules, allowing randomness and free-will to play together.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small amount of randomness is essential to life otherwise it becomes monotonous. This randomness acts as an antifragile agent. But too much of volatility is detrimental hence a balance must be maintained. Its just like vaccine doses: Build up immunity by small doses of infections but a large infection will probably kill you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extremistan vs Mediocristan: Extremes vs mediocrities: A dentist has a limited income, and all dentists in a definite geographical area would have a “ranged” income. Au contraire, an author can have potentially unlimited income. However such authors are rare. An average dentist earns similar to or perhaps more than the average author. But on the extremes, some authors live in penury and some in mansions. Corollary: Scandals never hurt artists because they are in extremistan and the unbounded information flow can potentially open up opportunities. Corollary: Having a small “tribe” of followers and huge number of critics is more beneficial than everyone saying your work is “good”. Again, because of how extremes behave.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Respecting the ancient: What has survived for long is more likely to survive for longer(Lindy Effect). People create rituals and religions as a means to an end. Take that away and chaos ensues. Besides, what people “believe” and “do” are vastly different, as in the Pope wouldn’t go to the church instead of the doctor in case of a medical problem. Survival is essential for science, not the other way around. To avoid clashes of cultures, Commerce and trade is one easy way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently finished reading the “Incerto”, a multi-volume part autobiography and part exploration of chance, randomness, probability and luck, written by Nassim Nicholas Taleb. The title of this article sounds provocative as it should be. Its difficult to distill “essence” of multi-volume books in a short listicle. But this article’s telos is to document my own personal insights and learnings that I have gathered by reading Taleb’s books.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Installing the Fastai library on Windows 10</title><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/06/03/fastai-windows.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Installing the Fastai library on Windows 10" /><published>2020-06-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/06/03/fastai-windows</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/06/03/fastai-windows.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;installing-the-fastai-library-on-windows-10&quot;&gt;Installing the Fastai library on Windows 10&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the steps I took to install fastai v2 on my windows machine. This version of fastai is still in development as of 3rd of June,
2020 so I would recommend using v1 instead for production. (But then, would you use windows for production ? ;) )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-the-instructions-at-httpsdevfastai-to-install-an-editable-version&quot;&gt;Use the instructions at https://dev.fast.ai/ to install an editable version&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/fastai/fastai2
cd fastai2
conda env create -f environment.yml
source activate fastai2
pip install -e &quot;.[dev]&quot;

git clone https://github.com/fastai/fastcore
cd fastcore
pip install -e &quot;.[dev]&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above commands should install both fastai and fastcore in editable mode. So, if you update one, remember to update the other as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heres-what-i-tried-after-installing&quot;&gt;Here’s what I tried after installing:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;from fastai2.vision.all import *
path = untar_data(URLs.PETS)/'images'

def is_cat(x): return x[0].isupper()
dls = ImageDataLoaders.from_name_func(
    path, get_image_files(path), valid_pct=0.2, seed=42,
    label_func=is_cat, item_tfms=Resize(224), num_workers=0)

learn = cnn_learner(dls, resnet34, metrics=error_rate)
from PIL import ImageFile
ImageFile.LOAD_TRUNCATED_IMAGES = True
learn.fine_tune(1)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an RTX 2060 in my machine and training took 256 seconds compared to Google Colaboratory which took 89 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-to-note&quot;&gt;Things to Note&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you see a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CUDA Runtime Error&lt;/code&gt;, set the  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;num_workers = 0&lt;/code&gt; in the dataloader function.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;OSError: Image file is truncated&lt;/code&gt; , use this piece of code
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;from PIL import ImageFile
ImageFile.LOAD_TRUNCATED_IMAGES = True
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would try to add more points here once I explore further.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Installing the Fastai library on Windows 10</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on Learning</title><link href="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/01/28/learning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Learning" /><published>2020-01-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-01-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/01/28/learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thepurplingpoet.github.io/blog/markdown/2020/01/28/learning.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;notes-on-learning&quot;&gt;Notes on Learning&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-absorb-information-faster-and-retain-for-longer&quot;&gt;How to absorb information faster and retain for longer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a compiled set of tools that I have gathered from various sources to help in the process of learning. You can 
use it as a framework to tackle any learning assignment. There are a ton of material out there and I have included only the
ones that have helped me immensely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;before-study&quot;&gt;Before Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design a near-optimal environment that you’re comfortable with.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try Airplane mode on phone.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try noise-cancelling headphones.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try ambient background music to help in concentration (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.noisli.com&quot;&gt;noisli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brain.fm&quot;&gt;brain.fm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://coderadio.freecodecamp.org/&quot;&gt;freecodecamp-radio&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design the study sessions along the lines of &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/deliberate-practice-theory&quot;&gt;Deliberate practice&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Find material which is not too easy, nor too hard but at a level that pushes you to exercise your brain without requiring advanced skills.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Model your self-education around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fast.ai/2016/10/08/teaching-philosophy/&quot;&gt;these principles&lt;/a&gt;. Diversify your resources.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Focus on applications first when starting out, then learn the theory as and when needed. Example: If you’re trying to learn Deep Learning, try building some models first and then learn the theory behind it, as taught in the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;course.fast.ai&quot;&gt;Fast.ai course&lt;/a&gt;.
Another example: If you’re trying to learn a second language, try speaking useful phrases before learning grammar.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Learn by doing. Build things. Get actively involved in the process.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;during-study&quot;&gt;During Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Divide your study sessions into chunks of 25 minutes of focused work followed by 5 minutes of break. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&quot;&gt;Pomodoro method&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forestapp.cc/&quot;&gt;Forest app&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take notes while you study. Type/write the words out in your note-taking app/notebook instead of copy-pasting or capturing images.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simultaneously create flashcards to use spaced-repetition. &lt;a href=&quot;https://quantum.country&quot;&gt;This website on learning quantum computing&lt;/a&gt; incorporated spaced-repetition into the learning material. You can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.ankiweb.net/&quot;&gt;Anki&lt;/a&gt; for your personal notes. The app would take care of your repetitions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to incorporate visual mnemonics while learning. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nelsondellis.com/remember-it&quot;&gt;Nelson Dellis’ excellent book&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLnoNZatRUaRwFphlCMbwJeXuYg-AoE6t1&quot;&gt;his youtube channel&lt;/a&gt; will get you covered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most importantly, &lt;strong&gt;Pause and Ponder&lt;/strong&gt; (a phrase taken from videos by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.3blue1brown.com/&quot;&gt;Grant Sanderson&lt;/a&gt;). Think in analogies and reflect on the intuitive meaning to deepen the conceptual understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;after-study&quot;&gt;After Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review often. If you use Anki, this will be taken care of automatically. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://augmentingcognition.com/ltm.html&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jackkinsella.ie/articles/janki-method-refined&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. If you don’t use Anki or any spaced-repetition software, schedule your reviews in 1, 3, 7, 21, 45, … days. (This is what I used before moving to Anki. You can try your own schedules.) See &lt;a href=&quot;https://collegeinfogeek.com/spaced-repetition-memory-technique/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourawesomememory.com/spaced-repetition-overview/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recall trumps re-reading. When you’re reviewing, try to recall the material instead of just reading/watching/listening it again. Familiarity gives us a false sense of knowledge. Test yourself while reviewing to help in retention. Barbara Oakley’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://barbaraoakley.com/books/a-mind-for-numbers/&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn/&quot;&gt;course&lt;/a&gt; are amazing resources which delve deep into this concept and other study techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/2012/04/feynman-technique/&quot;&gt;Feynman technique&lt;/a&gt; for reinforcing what you learned:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pretend you are teaching it to a student.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Identify gaps in your explanation;  Go back to the source material, to better understand it. Also, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_f-qkGJBPts&quot;&gt;see this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to apply what you’ve learned to concrete problems to help cement your concepts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have fun learning!!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Notes on Learning How to absorb information faster and retain for longer</summary></entry></feed>